Leah: Earlier in this session we talked about
the different elements of software maintenance.
Let’s now look at the ‘improvements’ that can
be made during maintenance, and the potential
negative consequences that this may have.
Chris: Preventive software maintenance
As we have mentioned previously, ‘Preventive
Maintenance’ refers to software changes
carried out to futureproof a product and
prepare for any potential changes ahead.
This includes making code easier to scale
or maintain and managing legacy content.
It also covers finding and fixing
latent faults in the product before
they evolve into operational faults.
Leah: ‘Preventive software maintenance’
mainly takes place behind the scenes
and relates more to tidying and
preparation, rather than major changes.
Users of the software are unlikely to notice
preventive software changes directly, but
they may see the positive effect later.
This is because preventive maintenance
can mean the smoother implementation of
large-scale changes further down the line.
However, a negative consequence of this may
be the introduction of new bugs or errors that
may go undetected and affect functionality.
Chris: Corrective software maintenance
Corrective changes in software maintenance
fix bugs and defects in the software.
These are often carried out by implementing
quick, small updates as and when required.
Users are less likely to give negative feedback
as they will be happy any issues or bugs are
fixed making their experience smoother, as well
as making a system or application more reliable.
Leah: There may, however, be occasions when a
corrective fix may cause some disruption to users.
Imagine if a bug or flaw in the software
has been present for some time and the user
has grown used to its presence and therefore
adapted their behaviour to accommodate the flaw.
Fixing the issue may mean that they
will again have to change their
behaviour leading to negative feedback.
A corrective change may upset a user if they
have problems with a certain bug or flaw
which isn’t fixed when other issues are.
Chris: With corrective software maintenance,
it’s important to work fast and frequently which
will help to minimise any potential user problems
and keep your product working as expected.
Leah: Adaptive software maintenance
The tech environment is constantly changing.
New knowledge, hardware, and cybersecurity threats
mean that software quickly becomes outdated.
‘Adaptive software maintenance’
addresses this issue.
Adaptive changes focus on the
infrastructure of the software.
They’re made in response to new operating
systems, new hardware, and new platforms,
to keep the program compatible.
Chris: Adaptive software changes tend to be
low impact for users as they deal with the
internal workings of the software such as
making sure it can integrate with new tech.
Users may notice a small improvement in speed
or scalability but are otherwise unaffected.
Users are, however, more likely to notice when
adaptive maintenance isn’t completed, as it
may mean their software stops working on their
devices or they encounter compatibility issues.
Leah: Perfective software maintenance
Perfective software maintenance is the
biggest category as it addresses the
functionality and usability of the software.
It involves changing existing product
functionality by refining, deleting, or adding new
features and as well as changing the way a product
works, it might also change the way it looks.
This may impact and change the user
interface or in-app user journey.
Chris: The scope and visibility of these changes
make perfective maintenance the most likely
to generate a negative response from users.
Users won’t notice a bit of refactored
back-end code, but they will notice
any changes that are clearly visible in
the way the product looks and performs.
Managing perfective changes means communicating
with your users to emphasis the positives and
mitigate any potential negative sentiment.
This can be done by advertising, offering support
and responding effectively to product feedback.